<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/blog</id>
    <title>Manifold Docs Blog</title>
    <updated>2020-10-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Manifold Docs Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/favicon/favicon.svg</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Next Steps]]></title>
        <id>manifoldnextsteps</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldnextsteps"/>
        <updated>2020-10-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The digital publication platform Manifold Scholarship will enter a new phase of its development, supported by two major grants, one from The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation and one from the National Endowment for the Humanities, allowing Manifold to solidify its structure for future sustainability and to expand its work as a leading provider of digital Open Educational Resources (OERs). Manifold, a collaboration between the GC Digital Scholarship Lab at the CUNY Graduate Center, Cast Iron Coding, and the University of Minnesota Press, is an open-source platform that enables publishers to create media-rich, interactive digital publications and extend the educational benefits and access of this scholarship to more communities. “Manifold is an innovative platform that exemplifies the University’s vision of integrated research and teaching,” says Chris Cramer, Vice President for Research at the University of Minnesota.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Access Granted]]></title>
        <id>accessgranted</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/accessgranted"/>
        <updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are delighted to announce the release of Manifold version 5.0, which is available for download here! The centerpiece of this release, a new Access Controls feature, will allow users to limit access to selected projects on a Manifold installation.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy holidays from Manifold!]]></title>
        <id>happyholidaysfrommanifold</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/happyholidaysfrommanifold"/>
        <updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here's to 2019! The Manifold Team sends good wishes to all as we head into the shortest day of the year and turn toward 2020. I've asked each team member to share a good memory from the year, a Manifold gift (be it moment with someone in the community, a favorite feature, a resolution). We're happy to be working together and with all of you.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Affordable Learning Georgia]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightaffordablelearninggeorgia</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightaffordablelearninggeorgia"/>
        <updated>2019-11-21T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the last training of the season, Terence met with Jeff Gallant, Program Manager of Affordable Learning Georgia; Joy Woodson, Assistant Director for Marketing Communications; and Lucy Harrison, Assistant Vice Chancellor for Library Services and Executive Director of GALILEO.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: University of Georgia Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightuniversityofgeorgiapress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightuniversityofgeorgiapress"/>
        <updated>2019-11-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[watercolor illustration of UGA Press logo and UMinn gopher holding Manifold logoLast week, Manifold Digital Projects Editor Terence was at the University of Georgia Press—the oldest and largest publisher in Georgia—exploring new digital initiatives and publishing models with Director Lisa Bayer and Executive Editor of Scholarly and Digital Publishing Mick Gusinde-Duffy.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Black Women and Religious Cultures]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightblackwomenandreligiouscultures</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightblackwomenandreligiouscultures"/>
        <updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[&nbsp;]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Arte Publico Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightartepublicopress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightartepublicopress"/>
        <updated>2019-10-23T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[​Arte Público Press logo and watercolor gopher holding Manifold mugIn this post, we find our digital projects editor, Terence, traveling to Houston, Texas, to meet with the Arte Público Press digital team: Executive Editor Gabriela Baeza Ventura, Carolina Villarroel of the Recovering the US Hispanic Literary Heritage Project, and Digital Programs Manager Lorena Gauthereau. The conversation revolved primarily around their recovery mission, the presses digital initiatives, as well as intro publications aimed at younger members of the Latino community. And, of course, all the amazing cuisine that Houston has to offer. ​]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Lapham's Quarterly]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightlaphamsquarterly</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightlaphamsquarterly"/>
        <updated>2019-10-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Watercolor illustration of raccoon and gopher imitating Lapham's logo JanusThis week brought Terence from one Manifold hub to another, New York City, to meet with Elizabeth Della Zazzera, Digital Producer, and Jaime Fuller, Web Editor, at Lapham’s Quarterly.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Intermezzo]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightintermezzo</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightintermezzo"/>
        <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Watercolor gopher illustration holding Manifold and Intermezzo logosIn this post, we find our digital projects editor, Terence, traveling to the University of Kentucky to meet with Intermezzo editors Jeff Rice, Eric Detweiler, and Sergio C. Figueiredo. The conversation revolved around integrating Manifold with their series, which encourages writers to experiment with form, style, content, and approach to break down the barrier between the scholarly and the creative. Reviewing the work that Jeff and his team had undertaken in preparation for the meetings, Terence clearly saw that Intermezzo was fully invested in exploring and breaking boundaries. Already online was a research project analyzing the content of Amazon Mechanical Turk (MTurk) job posts to trace how they rhetorically depict human actants. Made up of a series of brief texts and Google On Air Hangouts between senior scholars, this project demonstrates the kind of investigative and creative project that Manifold enables. Even after all their work ahead of the meetings, the Intermezzo team was glad to have had Terence come down for the in-person training. While we’ve worked from the beginning to make the system as intuitive as possible, Manifold affords so much functionality beyond the obvious that having a guided and dedicated dive into its capabilities really makes a difference. “With this team already so well versed in the platform, we were able to focus in on the ways Manifold could streamline their existing production processes and explore new tactics they could leverage, depending on the needs of a particular project. With Manifold’s versatility, authors and editors have a range of editorial options available to them that are really fun to plumb in this kind of group setting.” Terence’s report suggests that much of what they discussed will be portable. “It was exciting to hear how the themes we discussed could be used not only in relation to Manifold but also in their respective classrooms—from emerging trends in digital scholarship to finding ways within their institutions to make scholarly content more readily accessible and financially viable for students.”]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Version 4.0 Overview]]></title>
        <id>manifoldversion40overview</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldversion40overview"/>
        <updated>2019-09-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Manifold team is delighted to announce the release of Manifold version 4.0. The hallmark features for this release are the addition of reading groups, which allow readers to annotate texts publicly, privately, or anonymously, and standalone mode, which allows creators to set up projects that appear without the library. We've also made notable strides in improving Manifold's accessibility and are now publishing docker images to Docker Hub.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: MESH at Michigan State University]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightmeshatmichiganstateuniversity</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightmeshatmichiganstateuniversity"/>
        <updated>2019-09-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This week we find our trusty digital projects editor on the road in East Lansing with Kathleen Fitzpatrick, Scott Schopieray, Kelly Sattler, and members of MESH at Michigan State University.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Fembot Collective]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightfembotcollective</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightfembotcollective"/>
        <updated>2019-09-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[illustration of Ada Lovelace holding Manifold logoThis week we find our digital projects editor with the managing members of the Fembot Collective, led by Radhika Gajjala at Bowling Green State University in Bowling Green, Ohio.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Gallaudet University Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightgallaudetuniversitypress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightgallaudetuniversitypress"/>
        <updated>2019-09-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this installment of Travels with Terence, we find our resident digital projects editor still in Washington, DC, turning his attention from George Washington University eastward to the Gallaudet University Press.The Gallaudet University Press, whose advocacy for the deaf community aligns with Manifold’s commitment to supporting scholarship across forms and modes of communication, was prepped and ready for Terence’s visit: Deirdre Mullervy, GUP’s managing editor, had already loaded four projects of their projects into the system prior to his arrival (and secured some of the yummiest banana bread around)!]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: George Washington University]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightgeorgewashingtonuniversity</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightgeorgewashingtonuniversity"/>
        <updated>2019-09-09T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to a new season of the Travels with Terence series! We pick up following our digital projects editor as he tours the country, conducting in-person training for the Manifold pilot program.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Pilot 2019–20]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicespilot201920</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicespilot201920"/>
        <updated>2019-06-06T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[MINNEAPOLIS, MN (June 6, 2019)—The Manifold team is pleased to announce the selection of the following ten organizations to participate in the second year of the Manifold Digital Services pilot program:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Version 3.0 Overview]]></title>
        <id>manifoldversion30overview</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldversion30overview"/>
        <updated>2019-04-10T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Manifold team is delighted to announce the release of Manifold version 3.0. The hallmark feature for this release is the addition of project content blocks, which provides editors the ability to customize the content that appears on project landing pages.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Pilot Spotlight: Concordia University Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicespilotspotlightconcordiauniversitypress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicespilotspotlightconcordiauniversitypress"/>
        <updated>2019-04-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is part 11 of the Travels with Terence series, following our digital projects editor on his pilot press in-person training program. Bee and gopher by Jojo Karlin Last week Terence was in Montreal, Quebec, meeting with the three-person staff of Concordia University Press, which was established in 2016 and will this fall publish its first books.“It's exciting for a new scholarly publisher like Concordia University Press to be a part of this pilot,” noted interim director Geoffrey Little. “We look forward to learning how Manifold can help us publish our peer-reviewed open-access books.”Despite priding himself as being directionally adept, Terence found himself a bit misplaced when he made his way to the Webster Library—home of the press—for the first sessions of the trip. “I was a bit early, and as I was making my way around a woman who had walked past me just a moment prior called out my name. It was Meredith Carruthers, the press’s Editorial and Production Coordinator; she recognized me from my email avatar. That was definitely a first, especially given how bad I am at making avatars of myself.”After introductions and a brief tour, Terence led Meredith and the press’s intern Charles on a guided tour of the platform, beginning with its origins and aims, demoing its present capabilities, and concluding with a review of the roadmap for future development. “I always love doing this opening session because it really reveals what the system is and serves as a catalyst for so many of the discussions that come in the later sessions.”"" What a fantastic space the Webster Library provided. Rich with color, and featuring high ceilings and interesting design choices that catch the eye—especially all the living plants that adorned the walls—made this such an ideal place to do our work. ""Geoffrey caught up with Meredith and Terence for lunch, where they had the chance to talk about their backgrounds and what brought them to publishing before they pivoted back to the library for a couple of sessions considering workflow and discovery and presentation. Terence remarked:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: University of Washington Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightuniversityofwashingtonpress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightuniversityofwashingtonpress"/>
        <updated>2019-03-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is part 10 of the Travels with Terence series, following our digital projects editor on his pilot press in-person training program."" Manifold mascots by Jojo Karlin Last week Terence was in Seattle, Washington, meeting with groups from the University of Washington Press and Libraries. Due to Washington’s interest in Manifold as a tool for Open Educational Resources (OER), and more generally for classroom use, Terence was joined by Krystyna Michael, Open Educational Technologist at the Graduate Center, CUNY. The University of Washington team, spearheaded by Beth Fuget at the press and Elliott Stevens, Verletta Kern, and Liz Bedford from the library side, welcomed Terence and Krystyna for a few days of meetings. After landing on Monday, Terence and Krystyna had a whirlwind tour of the press (with homemade scones) where they ran a quick demo of Manifold for Press Director Nicole Mitchell and the bulk of the editorial team. They then made for the library where they introduced Manifold’s main features before discussing how to structure projects, curate content, map project development, and work with authors from teaching and publishing perspectives. They finished (amid cookies) with a close review of the development roadmap, an exploration of how other institutions are using Manifold, and how Manifold is situated against other players in the community. "" Looking out over the city and campus, with Mount Rainier in the background, from UW Tower. A theme that emerged from those discussions is how, rather than a centralized system that dictates its use, Manifold is a flexible tool that individual institutions can—and are expected to—make their own. At the same time, Manifold fosters a community for the institutions and individuals who use it to rely upon and with whom to explore questions collaboratively.Tuesday opened with a refresher introduction for those unable to attend Monday, before progressing into sessions focusing on how Manifold is already being used in the classroom, both at CUNY and Washington. Terence noted that “those sessions were the highlight of the trip for me. It was utterly invaluable to have Krystyna there in person leading those discussions and talking about her experiences using Manifold as a pedagogical tool and speaking to the privacy and legal questions and constructs that come up around such use. And to then have an instructor from Washington come up with his students and share their experiences using the platform to enable their scholarship—it was really powerful and inspiring. I felt it, and I’m certain Matt did too,” referring to Matt Gold, Manifold’s co-PI who remoted in from New York to speak alongside Krystyna."" A view of the beautiful Suzzallo Library at the heart of campus. And if that wasn’t already a big day, Terence and Krystyna finished off with a three-plus-hour tour of how to push Manifold to its limits without cracking open the command line interface (CLI). “We left any talk of the CLI to Zach on Wednesday,” Terence said, speaking of Manifold’s lead developer, Zach Davis, who led a remote session from Cast Iron Coding’s Portland offices on Wednesday, digging deep into the underlying structure and architecture of the system while also tackling important questions about accessibility. Ahead of these training sessions, Washington’s Accessibility Office did a thorough review of Manifold and provided nuanced notes to help expand on the work Zach’s team had done in this area last summer. Enabling Manifold to be as accessible as possible is a core tenet of Manifold’s ongoing development plans, so it was quite the coup to receive expert advice from Washington’s office, which regularly works with clients like Microsoft and Google.Closing out the trip, Terence commented,]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Reanimate Publishing]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightreanimatepublishing</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightreanimatepublishing"/>
        <updated>2019-03-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is part 9 of the Travels with Terence series, following our digital projects editor on his pilot press in-person training program.watercolor illustration of gopher with reanimate and Manifold logosThis March brought Terence to Salem, Massachusetts, to meet with Reanimate Publishing. Reanimate is co-directed by Roopika Risam, Assistant Professor of English and Faculty Fellow for Digital Library Initiatives, Salem State University and Carol Stabile, Associate Dean of Strategic Initiatives and Professor of Women and Gender Studies, University of Oregon.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Liverpool University Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightliverpooluniversitypress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightliverpooluniversitypress"/>
        <updated>2019-02-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is part 8 of the Travels with Terence series, following our digital projects editor on his pilot press in-person training program.cartoon of gopher holding Manifold book in front of Liverpool U crest and mottoIn one of his first dispatches from Liverpool, Terence noted to the team back home:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: The University of the West Indies Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlighttheuniversityofwestindiespress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlighttheuniversityofwestindiespress"/>
        <updated>2019-02-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is part 7 of the Travels with Terence series, following our digital projects editor on his pilot press in-person training program.watercolor illustration of a pelican and gopher with books and Manifold iconsLast week Terence was ensconced at home in Minneapolis at the heart of the polar vortex, learning first hand what a wind chill of fifty below felt like. This week he fled&nbsp;journeyed to Kingston, Jamaica to meet with the good folks from the University of the West Indies Press, where the Manifold program is being led by the press's management team]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Emory Center for Digital Scholarship]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightemorycenterfordigitalscholarship</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightemorycenterfordigitalscholarship"/>
        <updated>2019-01-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[‎This is part 6 of the Travels with Terence series, following our digital projects editor on his pilot press in-person training program.cartoon sketch of Emory eagle and UMinn gopher with books and Manifold mugLast week Terence set off on his first trip of 2019, journeying to Atlanta to meet with faculty and staff across Emory University. Unlike other pilot programs, Manifold at Emory isn’t centered around a university press or library. Instead the initiative is being spearheaded by Sarah McKee of the Bill and Carol Fox Center for Humanistic Inquiry and Wayne Morse, Allen Tullos, and Yang Li of the Emory Center for Digital Scholarship, for use by students and faculty with local projects and programming and as a means to introduce the community at large to new modes of publication that publishers with whom local scholars may already be working can take advantage. A fantastic space for training. Participants could use local machines to explore freely, and having two screens as a presenter is always quite the coup.When they heard they were selected for the first pilot round, the Emory team noted that &nbsp;“Manifold offers an intuitive and consistent experience for digital monograph publication, scholarship, and readership. We are excited that it is professionally maintained with design and sustainability in mind.”And that’s a thread which persisted through training. As we discussed his trip, Terence said,]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold in Portland: The Grateful Fed]]></title>
        <id>manifoldinportlandthegratefulfed</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldinportlandthegratefulfed"/>
        <updated>2018-12-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This month the combined team had our face-to-face at the Cast Iron Coding offices in Portland, Oregon, where our hosts managed to feed us both Portland culture and delicious food and get through an agenda packed with tricky topics and complicated concerns. Mt. Hood from above Minnesota and New York trickled into PDX Wednesday to crystal blue skies and brilliant sunlight illuminating Mt. Hood. After some Powell’s pilgrimages and art museuming, we met up at Ringler’s for casual convening. Even the requisite Grateful Dead cover band couldn’t keep conversation off the forthcoming questions of preservation, pilot projects, and bug-fix workflows. &nbsp;  Terence, Dan, Susan, Doug, Zach, and Matt at Ringler’s cellar bar &nbsp;  Susan, Doug, Dan, Matt, and Terence arriving at Washington High School aka Revolution Hall Those of us traveling west got up early and got in some work in the hotel library (surprise surprise—a bunch of book nerds felt cozy by the fire and book-lined walls) before we made our way to the Cast Iron Coding office. Cast Iron lives in the former Washington High School, now called Revolution Hall, and the open floor plan is friendly and pin-drop quiet. Cast Iron team members who work on Manifold, including the seemingly inexhaustible Max Ono, as well as canine representatives Rowan and Ida, dropped in at key moments. &nbsp;]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: University of Cincinnati Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightuniversityofcincinnatipress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightuniversityofcincinnatipress"/>
        <updated>2018-12-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is part 5 of the Travels with Terence series, following our digital projects editor on his pilot press in-person training program. Jojo illustrates the Cincy Bearcat and UMinn gopher. At the University of Cincinnati Press, Manifold is in the capable hands of Elizabeth Scarpelli, Press Director. Terence headed to Cincinnati almost immediately on the heels of the team’s Portland face-to-face (recap blog post to follow), so he was well primed to address their hopes and challenges.University of Cincinnati sign on a bench in front of a building and trees Following their last training session, Terence and Sean made a final coffee run, which took them past the entrance to the university. When selected for the Manifold Digital Services Pilot, Liz said:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Temple University Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlighttempleuniversitypress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlighttempleuniversitypress"/>
        <updated>2018-12-06T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is part 4 of the Travels with Terence series, following our digital projects editor on his pilot press in-person training program.Illustration of an owl wearing a Temple University logo and a gopher with a UMinn Press tote as papers around them transform into Manifold logos &nbsp; This week brought Terence to Temple University Press in Philadelphia! Given his American Ninja Warrior tendencies, he’d planned to run the “Rocky stairs” at the art museum, but after a recent injury, he opted to spend that time resting and recuperating over a lovely Indian dinner.The Manifold pilot at Temple is being spearheaded by Mary Rose Muccie, Director, Temple University Press and Scholarly Communications Officer, Temple University Libraries, and Annie Johnson, Library Publishing and Scholarly Communications Specialist, Temple University Libraries. Terence had the chance to meet with both and remarked:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Indiana University Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightindianauniversitypress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightindianauniversitypress"/>
        <updated>2018-11-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Watercolor illustration of Indiana non-mascots, a bulldog and a bison, with UMinn gopher standing on a stack of papers Minnesota gopher, Indiana bulldog and bison publishing -- a doodle by Jojo This is part 3 of the Travels with Terence series, following our digital projects editor on his pilot press in-person training program. The Indiana Memorial Union houses the Biddle Hotel and the Chocolate Moose. In honor of University Press Week (#TurnitUP), we’re spotlighting our most recent Manifold Digital Services Pilot—Indiana University Press! Spearheaded by Michael Regoli, Director of Publishing Operations, the Indiana team dove deep into Manifold this week. A plaster cast of Jean-Baptiste Carpeaux’s Ugolina and His Sons, (1861) awaits those entering the Indiana Memorial Union. Upon first joining the Manifold Digital Services Pilot Regoli remarked:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold on DigitalOcean]]></title>
        <id>manifoldondigitalocean</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldondigitalocean"/>
        <updated>2018-11-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[digital ocean and manifold logos with caption "do it yourself installation"Dear Manifold community!We are always working to make it easier to use Manifold at all levels. To this end, we teamed up with the DigitalOcean community to make the process of installing Manifold on your own even easier.Check out our new post, "How To Install and Set Up Manifold Scholar,"&nbsp;on their website!&nbsp;Follow the streamlined tutorial to get Manifold up and running on your own DigitalOcean Droplet.As ever, we invite your questions, your stories, your involvement. Follow along on Github for more details and to request features. Feel free to reach out on the community Slack channel or tweet us at @manifoldscholar. &nbsp;]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Athabasca University Press]]></title>
        <id>manifolddigitalservicesspotlightathabascauniversitypress</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightathabascauniversitypress"/>
        <updated>2018-10-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Travels with Terence, Part 2]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Project Collections]]></title>
        <id>introducingprojectcollections</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/introducingprojectcollections"/>
        <updated>2018-10-10T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[A hand holding a blank book object in front of Manifold's Featured Project icon with text that reads "Hmmmm.... we could feature projects about voting! Or prepare our collection for the upcoming conference and showcase new titles... what will your Manifold homepage display?" Entering a new world of choice on Manifold]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Travels with Terence]]></title>
        <id>travelswithterence</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/travelswithterence"/>
        <updated>2018-09-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[A cartoon sketch of Terence Smyre with travel gear and captions of what he is brining Because you’re someone who’s worked a lot building projects on Manifold, to get our interview started could you tell readers—what’s your favorite thing about Manifold? I like that we’re providing a platform for people who wouldn’t otherwise have one or would have to rely on a separate vendor. Zach and his team at Cast Iron have done a lot of work to make sure that Manifold is easy to use, and I think that’s crucial. I’m a big fan of bringing as much work in-house as you can and building up your own experience and knowledge base.&nbsp;With Manifold, publishers will have the ability to serve their materials on the web in an elegant way and make use of all the various forms of media the digital environment allows.I’m curious about your experience before Manifold? Can you tell us something about your time at Nebraska?I was at Nebraska for twelve-ish years, and I was in both the books and journals programs, but I primarily oversaw journals production. That involved working with journal editors and authors, evaluating manuscripts for structure, style, mechanics, and copyright concerns, coding manuscripts to our production system, preparing notes and directions for our freelance copy editors and our in-house typesetter, evaluating edits and proofs and corrections to them, and then working out print runs, etc. And I did some general business/budgetary stuff for those parts of the process I worked with. It was a lot, but it was a great team. I oversaw a typesetter dedicated to journals work and a project supervisor who I was glad to see take over for me when I left.So full cycle?Full cycle. I think when I was there we had thirty journals. Also, just before I left, we began working with Nebraska’s extension program and helping them with their publications. The extension publications are a really good use case for Manifold—often shorter documents, reports, created by experts in the field with outreach programs, all the way up to larger spiral bound publications.Your text-preparation experience at Nebraska was pretty soup to nuts?Yeah. It was fun. I was also part of a small team that helped implement Scribe’s Well-Formed Document Workflow for the press, changing over from a do-it-yourself coding system to a more regimented, structured XML workflow.So you were ready. You knew Manifold was the thing we needed.It’s funny, I remember in April 2015 when the press release went out about Manifold, I thought “this is what we should be doing—we should be doing this” and that if any position opened up, I was going to throw my hat in. Because there’s no way I couldn’t. When I saw the advertisement later that summer I was excited, but I also didn’t expect to get a call, because I was sure everyone and their brother would be banging down the door for the opportunity. It’s just too awesome. It’s worked out great for all of us.I feel very lucky. This is a dream job. I mean, where else do you get to work on such an important and far-reaching project with a team of just absolutely awesome people. We’ve built this amazing platform in just a few years, and we still are able to cover important questions like Beastmaster or Krull on Slack. It doesn’t get any better than that.Now that you’re starting to work with presses of different sizes, how do you adapt to different workflows? The big thing I’ve noticed is that getting to EPUB is not always an easy reach for some publishers. They can get to it, but it’s roundabout—exporting from InDesign or Google Docs—and they don’t have that same fundamental control over them or the experience of breaking into the EPUB and doing the fine tuning.For most university presses, that’s not going to be an issue—they’ll do it in house with Scribe or P-Shift or they’ll outsource it to a vendor who can do it for them. In those cases, you’re going to get something that works just fine. We’ve tested EPUB files from a host of different vendors, and we’ve never had any problem—they all work in Manifold. For smaller or newer publishers, getting to that point is not always as easy, which is why it’s so nice to have support for Word and Google Doc ingestion. Likewise for those willing to branch out to Markdown and HTML. Markdown, I think, is an easy reach, and if you’re open to that, that’s great. I’m all about the Markdown.Me, too!Really? Are you trying it?Yeah—I am working on a book for a friend because she teaches books that are out of copyright. Her class chose an early American novel, Hope Leslie, that has no EPUB but exists on the Internet Archive as a PDF and in OCRed plaintext. It’s super messy and I’m teaching myself how to structure it in Markdown. The plan is to get it up on CUNY Manifold so she can teach with it. If I trusted my ability to program, I’d run some scripts, but I’m mostly cleaning by hand.So you’re just taking the dirty OCR and running some scripts on it and making it look good?More like I am running find and replace.I’ve done that a lot of times—and even just doing that, I’ve found, is a big step up and often very useful for those around you. Most of the “scripts” I’ve written are simply just chains of find and replace.Which leads me to the question about smaller presses—for the presses that don’t have EPUB production built into their system, how much do you anticipate in terms of teaching?It’ll be a lot of prep work and dialoguing. Talking to all the pilot programs before I go out for my in-person training to see what their workflows look like and getting some sample files. I’m looking to craft a roadmap and a process that a publisher can easily use and replicate as a sort of touchstone that they can later spring from into more complex or creative uses of the platform. And hopefully during the training, we can work through the bulk of the big questions in person. After that I expect there will still be a host of fringe questions that we can take care of in a venue like this a web call] or in our&nbsp;[Slack channel. It’s really cool to have the #Pilot channel on Slack so that people who have similar sorts of approaches or levels of experience are able to interact directly with one another and get good practical feedback. Very cool! We advocate conversation and community.That’s the way you learn! It’s nice to be put in touch with others grappling with similar issues and to dynamically engage with those questions. A lot of times you don’t know who to talk to or reach out to, and to have that built into the fabric of our program is really cool.Can you give a list of technical skills or aptitudes that you think would be important for a Manifold editor at a press?Zach and his team have made it amazingly easy to get stuff into the system and looking beautiful. So the first response that bubbles up for me is to say something like, I don’t think you need a bunch of technical know-how . . .I’ve told people that it can help to have some familiarity with Markdown, a basic text editor, maybe Wordpress or some HTML.Yeah, that’s a more useful answer. I’d say CSS as well. If you’ve even done some cursory work with CSS or HTML, you’re going to be just fine. And really, all the heavy lifting will be in file prep. If for whatever reason you’re working with file types that Manifold can’t ingest natively, then it’s going to be about being willing to stretch yourself and not being afraid of technology. Nothing that anybody does is going to break anything. If you encounter problems, we’re going to be there to help. The big thing is not to be afraid, embrace the different tools that are available, cultivate a pioneering spirit, and just experiment. You don’t have to know exactly what you’re doing, but if you’re willing to throw yourself out there, then you’re going to be just fine. And more than likely you’re going to find it’s a lot easier than you expect. You might hit a few initial road bumps, but once you’ve cleared them you’ll see this is a lot different or easier and not as cumbersome as you imagined it to be. Especially with Manifold.It helps to have some understanding of where different operations take place.Oh definitely. And that guides us as we are creating documentation. It’s really important to understand how things are working and how you can affect what you’re seeing on screen. In a conference call recently I had a question about linked footnotes, and the person on the call asked if Manifold was automating that process, automatically creating a link between the text and the note. (Manifold isn’t doing that; it’s simply honoring the source document’s links.) That’s not clear when you’re just coming to this. So we are working really hard to make sure that those kinds of questions have good answers in our documentation. That if you aren’t sure how something works or how to change what you’re seeing, there’s an answer with clear steps you can take to get the results you want.So having some basic skills helps, but truly if you can create a document on a computer, you can create a Manifold project?Yeah. If you can navigate a web page and use a browser, working in Manifold isn’t harder than that.What do you anticipate with the presses to come? Do you have particular things you’re looking out for?I’m sure there will be lots of obstacles, but I’ll be doing my homework ahead of time so I can be as prepared as possible when I’m out there. I’m versed in Mac and PC systems, but it’s been awhile since I’ve used a PC—Nebraska was PC-based and I know a lot of university presses are—so I’m going to dust off my old desktop beforehand to make sure I’m fluent again with those systems. But then in terms of production, it’s going to be interesting to see where they’re leaving off Word, if they’re leaving off Word and getting to other document types. Because almost everyone we talked to can get to PDF, but as you know Manifold doesn’t do PDF in the reader. So what is the step before? And then exploring what they’re doing and how to get from there into Manifold. That’ll be interesting, but I don’t think it’s going to be difficult. I think it’ll be more about navigating the procedural nuances for the different houses.Do you have a sense of how many people will be in your training sessions?I’ll know beforehand. The first press, Athabasca, is around eight people, I believe. Usually it’ll be pretty production-oriented, but some will be coming from editorial and some will just be from different backgrounds who have the bandwidth and the gusto. When I go out, I’ll be doing a general overview for everyone so they have an idea of “what is this thing we signed up for?”, getting an appreciation for what Manifold can do for them and having the opportunity to ask questions, before breaking off into smaller focus groups. It tends to work best when you have eight to ten people crowding around a computer and a couple monitors—you can really get into the nitty gritty and get some good work accomplished that way.Do the presses have collections they have pinpointed? Most of them yes. Some have works coming down the pipe.Have you ever been to any of the presses before?Not a one!Have you been to any of the cities?I’ve been to Atlanta before. I’ve never been to Canada . . .You’ve never been to Canada? Who are you?The guy who’s never been to Canada. I’ve never been to the UK, and I’ve never been to Jamaica. I’ve not been to Temple. Have you been to Philadelphia?Yes. And I’ve run up the steps. And yes. I’ll be running up the steps again. I’ve been to Seattle, but not to the press.I’ve never been to Bloomington, Indiana, or Cincinnati. The only things I know about Cincinnati I learned from WKRP in Cincinnati—so not much.What will you read on the plane?I don’t know! I’m just finishing Don’t Look Behind You by Samuel Rogers. I’ve got a few books on the nightstand that will make good travel fare. I’ve never read the Harry Potter books.Ever?Ever. I read the first one not that long ago. It was really good! I have the second one just waiting for me.(At this point I recommended the Witch, Please podcast.)That sounds cool. I don’t know what else I’m going to queue up. Do you know of the Flavia De Luce books? I know of them—my mother shares my New York Public Library account and sometimes books just show up. I’m sure I’m going to have one or two of those. I know I’ve got a physics book. And Neil Gaiman’s Norse Mythology.Do you have any last things to say in preparation for Travels with Terence?I’m just really excited to get started. Really honored to have the chance to work with these publishers and help them use Manifold to produce some really exciting and important works.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Version 2.0 Overview]]></title>
        <id>manifoldversion20overview</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldversion20overview"/>
        <updated>2018-09-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Manifold team is delighted to announce the release of version 2.0 of the Manifold platform. This release adds new accessibility features, makes multiple improvements to the reading experience of Manifold, and expands the number of types of document formats that can be ingested by the platform. For details, please see below or watch this video overview:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ten publishers to begin using Manifold platform to publish scholarly work]]></title>
        <id>tenpublisherstobeginusingmanifold</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/tenpublisherstobeginusingmanifold"/>
        <updated>2018-08-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[MINNEAPOLIS, MN (August 30, 2018)—The Manifold team has selected the following ten groups to receive free installation and training on the Manifold platform to help them meet their digital publishing goals:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Preserving Manifold Editions: Topics of Consideration]]></title>
        <id>preservingmanifoldeditionstopicsofconsideration</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/preservingmanifoldeditionstopicsofconsideration"/>
        <updated>2018-08-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Digital preservation is a cornerstone issue for the Manifold team to address during our second phase. In creating a platform for publishers to collect and disseminate singular works that contribute to the scholarly record, it is imperative that we provide a means to preserve those works against the rigors of time and technological obsolescence. Publishers, authors, and the communities they serve need to be confident the materials they are publishing on Manifold will not only be discoverable, but also reliably accessible and useable for future engagement.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Meeting in Minnesota]]></title>
        <id>manifoldmeetinginminnesota</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldmeetinginminnesota"/>
        <updated>2018-08-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[July 11th through 13th, the Manifold team convened in sunny if stormy Minneapolis for three days of meetings to assess progress, make decisions about the Manifold Digital Services Pilot, plan steps toward the version 2.0 release, and, of course, try out the downtown food truck scene.photo of Matt and Zach and Terence happily gathered at the UMP office lobby Matt Gold, Zach Davis, and Terence Smyre at UMP The Minnesota crew—Doug, Susan, Terence, and Dan—plied us with coffee and pastry topped with Susan's homemade rhubarb jam as we set out Wednesday morning to tackle our hefty agenda. Zach ran through the progress Cast Iron Coding has made, walking us all through the road map on Github. Much of the recent development work has focused on improving accessibility standards and adding support for new formats (Word documents and LaTeX) that Manifold can ingest directly into the reader. In the roadmap discussion, we talked a lot about the different ways that publishers are using Manifold and about how project home pages, which are currently uniform, could become more flexible to accommodate those varying use cases.. We spent time discussing those use cases, determining what should they be called, and thinking through what they would comprise -- what, for instance, makes a journal a journal and not a multiple author open educational resource? Our thoughts on all of these matters have been informed and inspired by Manifold users, who have consistently come to us with questions and thoughts about how the platform can be expanded in new ways. As Niels-Oliver Walkowski said on Manifold’s public Slack channel, “The prospects look really exciting.”Looking ahead to version 3.0, Manifold has plans for project templates and theming. As the Cast Iron team continues to improve accessibility and ease of implementation for all users, we are also considering the balance between user control and user responsibility. Manifold has worked hard to establish a platform that is both flexible for publishers and streamlined enough to provide for a seamless and uniform user experience.Version 4.0 will focus on providing publishers the means to set up Manifold instances that are oriented around single projects, as an alternative to the default library view, where readers peruse a publisher's entire catalog. With the single-project setup, publishers will still have the ability to publish on Manifold as many projects as they would like, using only one backend interface. However, projects would now each have their own distinct web presence, allowing them to be more neatly nested into existing websites and offering those who only have a handful of projects for the platform the means to present them in a more appropriate way. Annotation groups—useful for classes or groups of readers who would like to comment on a text together—are also on deck for version 4.0. The team had a provocative conversation about what degree of administration and content moderation Manifold should accommodate. Peer review and classroom contexts had everyone thinking carefully about who monitors what and where.The conversation about preservation and programmatic ingestion slated for version 5.0 brought up a series of questions about what responsibility Manifold has to preserve its interactive components and primed us for our planned meeting with the Minnesota library team. The resource capabilities Manifold offers present the greatest challenges in terms of preservation. Not only do rich resources raise questions of simulation versus static preservation, but interactive content in the form of annotations and reader contributions also poses rights and copyright concerns. Would saving content for the authors and other readers require that Manifold users agree to a creative commons license before publishing any material or leaving any annotations on a text? Would Manifold need to support the moderation of such content? Read on for an overview of our library notes and stay tuned for Terence’s blog post addressing Manifold’s plans for preservation.Many notes were taken and issues were written before we made our way to the food truck alley. Turning the corner of an otherwise sensible-looking downtown, we came to the veritable parade of colorful trucks purveying everything from organic egg sandwiches to artisan tacos. We ate on the steps in the open air, enjoying each other’s company and talking of travels. Evidently there is a very cold lake near Portland and gauntlets may have been thrown for the next meeting.In the afternoon, we reconvened to discuss project collections. Much consideration was given to anything that required user input. Still pleased with James Baker’s comment that Manifold is “pleasingly unfussy,” the team is wary of anything that might introduce bothersome fuss.It’s been nice catching all the nice things people are saying as they try out version 1.0.With what energy remained, we talked through the Manifold Digital Services business model. We thought through what people seem most curious about with Manifold. Rather that reviewing features for new users, we want to refocus the conversation and start highlighting the problems Manifold solves for publishers.Thursday we met first at the Wilson Library with John Butler, Associate University Librarian for Data & Technology; Emma Molls, Publishing Services Librarian; Jon Nichols, Director of Digital Preservation and Repository Technologies; Kate McCready, Director of Content Services; Carol Kussmann, Digital Preservation Analyst; and Stacie Traill, Metadata Analyst. After Zach presented Manifold, nearly forgetting to demonstrate the share features to cite or link social media which drew exclamations of awe from all present, we dug deep into conversation about preservation. Meeting with the library team offered us not only the chance to talk about Manifold specifically, but also to learn more about library processes for preserving web-based content and to discuss how we might strategically position Manifold to work well with those processes and workflows.&nbsp;With expertise in the room from so many library departments, the Manifold team was able to ask what each anticipates from publishers and what resources they have to preserve interactive content. The conversation naturally turned to the broader philosophical concerns. What is the responsibility of preservation of a Manifold edition—how much interactivity must you preserve? what permissions would be needed to preserve annotations? what solutions are the libraries pursuing? We learned a bit about the University of Minnesota Libraries digital asset management and preservation solution, Rosetta, and about the best practices the libraries use for preserving a record of digital objects.a live sketch of the Manifold team at the UMN library meeting -- Susan Doerr, Doug Armato, Matt Gold, and Zach Davis. Jojo live sketches the Manifold team at the UMN library meeting -- Susan Doerr, Doug Armato, Matt Gold, and Zach Davis. We made our way next to Cafe Alma for a delicious lunch and coffee while we reviewed the wonderful applications for the Manifold Digital Services Pilot Program and considered the ways Manifold could work across the richly varied use cases.Back at the press office, Zach ran a demo for press employees. Everyone seemed excited with more smiles than questions. After knocking out some ideas for templates for Manifold projects, we were ready to end the day with a quick bite to eat at a local spot. We made it to the bistro around the corner before the downpour! Getting caught in the rain, we were surprised to be captivated by American Ninja Warrior, which happened to be broadcasting on the bar televisions. Feats of strength and ingenious maneuvers seem oddly appropriate to the hurdles and hijinks of digital edition development.An illustration of a pumpkin head clothed in Renaissance attire. Sometimes dummy text and makeshift categories show up in demos. When Zach passed over "Renaissance Pumpkins" in his demo, Jojo felt illustration was in order. On Friday, we regrouped and laid out the next steps and coming milestones. We dug into templates—what are the logical ways to present simple or enhanced books? &nbsp;Journals or Open Educational Resources? Resource-only projects? Conceiving user interactions for each case, we oscillated between the practical and the philosophical. What do these terms historically evoke and how does Manifold most easily accommodate both the conceptual and functional needs? With the combination of UMP team’s broad array of publishing experience, Matt’s deep familiarity with researchers’ needs, and Zach’s tactical ingenuity for development, we came to a list of templates, that should serve us well without overcomplicating the user experience. These include Simple Book, Enhanced Book, Journal or Collection from single source, Journal or Collection from multiple sources, OER or Teaching Resource, Report or Handbook, and Resource Only. Follow Manifold on Github to see the design progress.With version 2.0 rolling out soon, Terence hitting the trail for Digital Services trainings, the CUNY Manifold revving up to the edge, everyone’s got a lot going on before we meet again in November in Portland. Releases, and campus visits, and OERs, oh my!Following an epic lunch of tacos -- and the necessary condiment of comparing hot sauce hotness -- Zach, Matt, and Jojo headed home to their opposite coasts, and Manifold carried on. To flagrantly misquote Harry Potter, Manifold managed.If you have any questions or comments or have thoughts on how American Ninja Warrior relates to scholarly publishing, please do chime in our Slack channel&nbsp;or tweet us at @manifoldscholar. &nbsp;]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Web Accessibility Roadmap for Manifold]]></title>
        <id>webaccessibilityroadmapformanifold</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/webaccessibilityroadmapformanifold"/>
        <updated>2018-08-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Web accessibility is a broad term used to describe any strategies, user interfaces, or content, specifically designed with assistive technologies (AT) and/or disabled users in mind. In developing the Manifold web app we strive for it to be as accessible as possible. Our particular focus is on the screen reader user experience. In this document we’ll explore the guidelines used in determining an acceptable level of accessibility, the best tools to aid in development, what AT compatibility pitfalls to avoid, and the strategies for continuing development. Hopefully this document will outline what work has been completed thus far, as well as describe some best practices for moving forward.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing the Release of Manifold 1.0]]></title>
        <id>announcingmanifold10</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/announcingmanifold10"/>
        <updated>2018-04-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[For those who didn't catch the press release in other media last month, it's worth saying again! The University of Minnesota Press with CUNY’s GC Digital Scholarship Lab and Cast Iron Coding announce the release of Manifold 1.0. MINNEAPOLIS, MN—The University of Minnesota Press, in partnership with the GC Digital Scholarship Lab at the Graduate Center of the City University of New York and digital development agency Cast Iron Coding, are pleased to announce the release of Manifold, a free, open-source platform to publish and read networked, interactive, media-rich books online. Manifold was developed from the ground up to integrate the publication of media-rich, networked monographs into existing university publication workflows. Publishers, and any group wanting to publish open-access works on the web, can quickly and easily turn existing files into online publications, through a robust ingestion system that can import texts from EPUB, HTML, Markdown, and Google Doc source files. Authors, working with their publisher, can easily enhance their projects with primary research documents and data, audio and video, links to archives, while engaging with readers and integrating social media conversations. Manifold also enables an iterative approach to publication so that authors can choose to share their work-in-progress as it develops. Doug Armato, Director of the University of Minnesota Press, says, “A goal of Manifold is to maintain professional scholarly publishing at the center of the emerging digital environment. We needed a scalable solution for media-rich monographs, social reading, faster digital publication, iterative and collaborative research and writing methods, as well as interoperability with digital humanities projects. We built Manifold with an eye toward the future when more and more scholars who publish print books will also want them to live, and be interacted with, on the internet.” Manifold is a mobile-friendly application that is compatible with all modern devices—smartphones, tablets, notebooks, and desktops. Readers have a beautiful, deep reading experience that encourages discussion and fosters community with the integration of social media. Four major beta versions of Manifold have been released to the public since development of the platform began in April 2015, culminating in Release 1.0 this week. Those wanting to install Manifold can find it at manifoldapp.org. During the three-year project, the Manifold team has spoken with university presses, institutes and centers, library publishing groups, and individual scholars, all who can use Manifold to publish the content produced by their group. Today there are three installations of Manifold, the University of Minnesota Press, CUNY, and the Mario Einaudi Center for International Studies at Cornell University, with the University of Arizona Press in the process of branding a Manifold installation to publish books for Open Arizona, an NEH and Andrew W. Mellon funded Open Book grant. Kathryn Conrad, Director of the University of Arizona Press, says, “Manifold exceeds our expectations for publishing open-access content on the web, offering many additional features than we had originally envisioned for our publication platform. We look forward to launching Open Arizona, powered by Manifold, in the coming months.” The Manifold team is currently focused on helping university presses and centers install the platform and on developing new features, including offering access-restricted use within classrooms or other small, private groups; serving a wider readership that includes people requiring assistive technology; and adding interoperability with other tools. Manifold is funded by a grant from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing Manifold Scholarship Phase Two]]></title>
        <id>announcingmanifoldscholarshipphasetwo</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/announcingmanifoldscholarshipphasetwo"/>
        <updated>2018-04-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The University of Minnesota Press with CUNY’s GC Digital Scholarship Lab and Cast Iron Coding to launch* MANIFOLD SCHOLARSHIP PHASE TWO *—with a $789,000 grant from The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation* Second phase will focus on expanding installations of the platform and developing new features* MINNEAPOLIS, MN (April 17, 2018)—The University of Minnesota Press in partnership with the GC Digital Scholarship Lab at The Graduate Center of The City University of New York, and digital development agency Cast Iron Coding has been awarded a $789,000 grant from The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation to launch phase two of Manifold Scholarship, an open-source web-based publishing platform that integrates the publication of media-rich, networked monographs into existing university press publication workflows. With this grant the Manifold Scholarship project will focus on assisting with installations at other institutions, further development of platform features, and a research project about potential OER (open education resources) uses of the platform. University of Minnesota President Eric Kaler says, “We take great pride in our press’s strong commitment to innovation and its productive, long-term partnership with such a leading digital humanities center as the GC Digital Scholarship Lab at the Graduate Center of the City University of New York. The results thus far have been impressive. That so many other presses and scholarly publishing venues at other institutions have expressed an active interest in adopting Manifold confirms our sense of the platform’s significant promise.” In May 2018, the Manifold partners will issue a call for applications from presses and institutions wanting assistance with getting started in using the Manifold platform. 20 (twenty) groups—10 in 2018, and 10 in 2019—will be selected by to receive free installation support and free on-site training to assist them in getting started using the platform. Doug Armato, University of Minnesota Press Director and Co-PI on the grant, says, “We are excited to have this opportunity to help other university presses, library publishing groups, and university centers install and get started in using the Manifold platform as part of their work to publish scholarship on the web. Working with twenty groups will allow the Manifold team to better understand the goals and needs of publishers who install the platform, and incorporate that feedback in our planning for Manifold’s future development.” Other priorities of Manifold’s phase two grant are enriching the reading experience for users of assistive technology, expanding the platform’s interoperability with other platforms, and a CUNY-led research project focused on open education resources (OER) uses of the platform. Matthew K. Gold, Associate Professor of English and Digital Humanities at The Graduate Center, CUNY and Co-PI on the grant, says, “Manifold has the potential to be a powerful platform for open digital pedagogy, allowing groups of students and faculty members to collaboratively read and annotate multimodal texts. OER initiatives have the potential to drive down textbook costs for students and we are particularly excited to work with Minnesota and CUNY librarians as we explore such uses for Manifold.” Development of Manifold Scholarship began in April 2015 culminating in Release 1.0 in March 2018. Publishers, and any group wanting to publish open-access works on the web, can quickly and easily turn existing files into online publications, through a robust ingestion system that can import texts from EPUB, HTML, Markdown, and Google Doc source files. About the platform//manifoldapp.org]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How To Code in Python: Using Manifold to Deliver an Open Educational Resource]]></title>
        <id>howtocodeinpythonusingmanifoldtodeliveranopeneducationalresource</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/howtocodeinpythonusingmanifoldtodeliveranopeneducationalresource"/>
        <updated>2018-03-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently, my eBook on Python programming, How To Code in Python 3, was made available as a Manifold publication. I would like to offer my perspective to the Manifold community to give some background on the work and how I believe the Manifold platform provides additional layers of value to the text through providing a place for learning and idea exchange in both university communities and broader publics. Python Manifold HeaderAs someone with an interdisciplinary academic background developed within public universities, making resources highly available and fostering communities have been strong focal points in my work. When I shifted trajectories to work in the technology industry while completing my PhD, it was important for me to continue to do work that contributed to the public good. What appealed to me about the cloud infrastructure provider DigitalOcean was that it was deeply committed to open source software development and knowledge sharing. I joined the Community team to help write and maintain their large archive of agnostic Creative Commons-licensed and open access technical tutorials that anyone could use to learn about programming and cloud infrastructure.When I joined the team, I worked exclusively on developing tutorials on the Python programming language. My efforts were largely based on my pedagogy training that focused on student-centered learning, my research with the CUNY Graduate Center’s Futures Initiative, and my own time as a university teacher. I designed a curriculum through learning Python’s logic and code syntax and worked with software developers and product designers in order to present the tutorial pathway in a way that could empower readers. Alongside this work, I produced project-based tutorials to guide readers through creating full working programs, and also worked with external community authors, including former academic colleagues and students like Michelle Morales and Jeremy Morris, to build out this resource.Python DevelopmentAlthough I designed these tutorials as something that could be read linearly if the reader chose to do so, I wanted to create pathways through the text that could encourage student-driven learning while also providing reference material for more experienced developers. When my team decided to package this material into a How To Code in Python_ eBook during an organization-wide hackathon, I thought that a book format may actually be somewhat counter-intuitive to my original intentions as it created a more sequential structure that was not as interactive as the tutorial series. This is why, when Matt Gold reached out to me regarding a publication of the book on CUNY’s instance of Manifold, I was excited about the possibilities.One of my earliest experiences with interactive online texts was Matt Gold’s own digital editions of Debates in the Digital Humanities. The opportunities afforded through making a fully online and open access version of the text and fostering the exchange of ideas speaks to the positive social impact that is possible through leveraging technology in community-driven ways. This is an especially significant gesture in the field of Digital Humanities, as inviting more people to the discussion can ensure that more communities are given access to not only engaging in the discourse, but to contribute to it as stakeholders.Manifold, an open source software project itself, is a platform that can contribute to several communities. As a publishing platform for academic material, it can bridge together scholars across disciplines as they create marginalia that opens broader discussions. It can also be used in the classroom and can be limited in scope so that a book used in a class can be made available only to enrolled students so that they can concentrate and learn together. Finally, platforms like Manifold can work to disrupt silos that prevent communication and understanding between academia and the larger public, by making scholarship more widely available and allowing more to enter the discourse. &nbsp; Follow Lisa Tagliaferri @lisaironcutter.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold v0.4.0]]></title>
        <id>manifoldv040</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldv040"/>
        <updated>2018-01-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I'm excited to announce that we're releasing v0.4.0 of Manifold today! This release ships with over 40 bug fixes, a few important security fixes, and a number of new features including backend UX updates, a new "your notes" interface in the reader that allows users to quickly jump to their highlights and annotations, and more editorial control over projects. The full list of enhancements is as follows:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold v0.3.0]]></title>
        <id>manifoldv030</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldv030"/>
        <updated>2017-10-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today, Friday the 13th, is your lucky day! I'm excited to announce that we have wrapped up development on version 0.3.0 of Manifold Scholarship. This version has been four months in the making, and includes a number of new features and bug fixes. As we move toward a stable 1.0.0 release, our focus has been on improving Manifold's performance and stability, and to that end we've managed to pack 85 documented bug fixes into this version.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold v0.2.0 Released]]></title>
        <id>manifoldv020released</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldv020released"/>
        <updated>2017-06-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[On behalf of the entire Manifold team, I'm super excited to announce the release of Manifold v0.2.0! The release is up on Github now, and we'll be rolling it out to our staging site later today. This release contains a number of new features and bugfixes, listed below. For the full list of revisions and pull requests, please consult&nbsp;the changelog.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold v0.1.3 released to staging.manifoldapp.org]]></title>
        <id>manifoldv013releasedtostagingmanifoldapporg</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldv013releasedtostagingmanifoldapporg"/>
        <updated>2017-04-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Version 0.1.3 of Manifold&nbsp;introduces support for logins&nbsp;using Facebook, Twitter, and Google OAuth services. This version also incorporates a refactored approach to managing application settings, which can now be set via the backend, or managed by way of the dotenv file, which tends to be a more appropriate solution for automated provisioning and deployment. Fixed bugs:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold v0.1.1 Released]]></title>
        <id>manifoldv011released</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldv011released"/>
        <updated>2017-04-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Version 0.1.1 of Manifold is a bugfix release. It has been pushed to the Manifold staging instance. This release includes the following fixes and improvements. [B] Reset default text color in dark reading mode [B] Only show FE mobile nav when logged in [C] Add spec test for resource event creation [B] Fix issue with broken link on first click [F] Create event when resource is added to project [B] Remove top spacing from section-heading-utility-right [C] Adjust sizing of event tiles [F] Add start reading link to new text events [B] Fix long file names overflowing dropzone [C] Use sub kind in slideshow to determine video type [C] Refactor resources to use sub kinds for better determination [B] Fire reader color change with 1 click (iOS) [B] Fix issue with resource markers not highlighting [B] Require library in formatted attr concern [B] Fix responsiveness of pagination controls [B] Use formatted text for applicable resource fields [C] Add disabled state to slideshow arrows [C] Hide social logins and T&C from create form [C] Change label on project backend form field [F] Store formatted attributes in Redis As always, B = Bugfix, F = Feature, and C = Chore.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Beta Now Available]]></title>
        <id>manifoldbetanowavailable</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldbetanowavailable"/>
        <updated>2017-04-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Manifold team is delighted to launch a public beta of its new publishing platform for interactive scholarly monographs//staging.manifoldapp.org/.browse-splashmanifold-devices-1Funded through the generous support of the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, Manifold is a collaboration between University of Minnesota Press, the GC Digital Scholarship Lab at the Graduate Center, CUNY, and Cast Iron Coding.We began work on the project two years ago, aiming to create a responsive platform for interactive books that would help university presses share long-form monographs through an appealing and elegant interface. After many meetings and planning discussions, and following 1300+ commits to our public code repository, the initial version of the platform is ready for review. On the beta site, you will find a selection of projects from the University of Minnesota Press that may be read, annotated, highlighted, and shared through social media. These include two recently published full-length scholarly books, a selection from the Forerunners]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold Preview!]]></title>
        <id>manifoldpreview</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldpreview"/>
        <updated>2017-03-31T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold is excited to announce the public launch of our&nbsp;in-progress demo next Tuesday, April 4th! In advance of that launch, we're happy to offer a&nbsp;brief preview of some of the features of this intuitive, collaborative publishing platform for scholars, made possible by a generous grant from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation. Manifold provides an online, mobile-ready interface&nbsp;for reading and responding to&nbsp;texts. The demo version will be populated by&nbsp;University of Minnesota Press books and projects, but any press or other organization can install the open-source platform and upload their own texts for interactive reading and annotation. For technical details about the build, check out posts by our lead developer, Zach Davis of Cast Iron Coding. Read on for your first sneak peek!browse-splashmanifold-devices-1]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading with Matthew K. Gold]]></title>
        <id>readingwithmatthewkgold</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/readingwithmatthewkgold"/>
        <updated>2017-01-09T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[mkgold-gc-15Before the holidays, I had the chance to chat with Manifold Co-PI Matthew K. Gold, who is Associate Professor of English and Digital Humanities and Executive Officer of the M.A. Program in Liberal Studies at the Graduate Center, CUNY. I have been lucky to work with Matt for a couple of years now, through seminars on digital humanities praxis and textual studies, on DH tool-building projects like DH Box, on the editorial collective of the Journal of Interactive Technology and Pedagogy, and with the digital fellows of the GC Digital Initiatives. His widespread commitment to textual scholarship and digital innovation, his seemingly tireless support of his students and digital experimentation, and his humility (which he may not even let me mention) never cease to amaze me. I have spent a lot of time discussing Manifold with Matt, but I was glad to get the chance to ask him more specifically about his personal motivations for developing a hybrid publishing platform.&nbsp; -- What matters most to you about Manifold? &nbsp;I think it’s the overall excellence&nbsp;of the user experience. Our goal is to create a platform that will rival the reading experience of a commercial site like Medium but that is free and open-source. I’m excited to see how various people will use it -- certainly our primary audience of university presses, but also a wider set of authors and publishers of all types. Cool. That sounds like a pretty noble mission to me.&nbsp; I’m also excited about our team -- we have the University of Minnesota Press, which is doing exciting experimentation on both its editorial and production sides -- &nbsp;it’s a Press that’s willing to take risks with the way it thinks about the future of publishing. Working with a partner like that -- and with Doug Armato and his team in particular -- is a lot of fun.. And then we are lucky to be collaborating with Cast Iron Coding-- Zach Davis and his team are extremely talented and very much aware of the latest trends in web development. Manifold won’t feel like a typical piece of academic technology, thanks to the work of Zach and his team. What’s your ideal reading experience?&nbsp; For me, print is still most important as a reading experience. But I’m never satisfied when I buy a printed book from a bookstore and then “that’s it.” I can’t carry all of my books with me when I go on a trip, so I really want both print and digital at the point of purchase. For me, if I’m going to read a book of theory or criticism, I’m going to be reading it in print, but I also want to be able to easily pull it up on my laptop or phone when I’m traveling or just happen to think of it during a meeting with a student, or I’m doing some writing and I want to refer to it. I want the materiality of the print book, but for access and reference, the online version. And Manifold is precisely about achieving that hybrid experience. So we are producing print books, but we are also creating web-based interactive texts that open up new collective and social reading experiences. What are you reading now?&nbsp; I am reading (and loving) Barbarian Days by William Finnegan.&nbsp;Somehow, reading about waves feels&nbsp;like the right thing in this post-election moment--an escape from politics but also a reminder of how to make our way among larger and sometimes brutal forces. Who inspires your work?&nbsp; I tend to be inspired by my academic mentors. My first academic mentor was Robert D. Richardson, Jr., who is a biographer of Thoreau and Emerson (his biography of Emerson remains one of my favorite books). I’m still in awe of his erudition and research and writing skills. I’m also inspired on a daily level by my colleagues at the Graduate Center and across CUNY, especially by the students I work with. --After Matt answered all the questions, we had the chance to speak more broadly about Manifold and the features that specifically address readers’ needs. The design of the platform -- from the icons, to commenting and annotation, to the reading interface -- is the result of careful consideration by a team of careful readers. Moving forward, even as I share more about the creators of Manifold and the reading practices that influence its development, I will be adding a features&nbsp;series to outline the thinking that goes into the various components of Manifold.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading with Zach Davis]]></title>
        <id>readingwithzachdavis</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/readingwithzachdavis"/>
        <updated>2016-12-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Zach Davis Zach Davis Last week, calling Portland from the Digital Scholarship Lab at the Graduate Center, I had the pleasure of speaking with Manifold’s lead developer, Zach Davis at Cast Iron Coding. Yet again, my attempts to record the call came to naught, but I will conjure some of the conversation from my notes.Zach is Principal Chief Technologist at Cast Iron Coding. His previous CIC projects include sites for the Hammer Museum in Los Angeles, The Edna McConnell Clark Foundation, the Jersey Give-Back Guide (check out the animation on the “generosity generator”) and Debates in Digital Humanities, a collaboration with The University of Minnesota Press and Matt Gold that served as a prototype for the Manifold project. Zach has been working steadily and seems rejuvenated by the team's recent Portland meeting. Talking through the next steps and considerations about how university presses will be able to customize Manifold installations seems to have crystallized the work that everyone has been doing in exciting ways.First, I asked Zach what matters most to him about Manifold. He noted the two most important things to him at this stage, made even more clear after the meeting.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[This Week in Manifold: Markdown and Backend Development]]></title>
        <id>thisweekinmanifoldbackend</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/thisweekinmanifoldbackend"/>
        <updated>2016-12-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Since I last posted, we've been making development progress on a few different fronts. Much of this work is still in feature branches, and has yet to be merged into the main development branch. Therefore, I'm going to skip the full list of revisions in this post, and instead offer a high level description of our recent efforts. Markdown and GitBook Support Fundamentally, Manifold has been conceived as a tool for university presses. When it comes to thinking about how it will be used, UMNP has guided our thinking about what problems presses are trying to solve, and how Manifold can help. That said, I think everyone on the project has also been interested in the ways in which Manifold can be a useful tool for the broader academic community. At the very least, we want to make it possible for individuals to find ways to use Manifold. One impediment to this, in my mind, has been the fact that to date Manifold only accepts finished EPUB documents as an input format, and independent scholars and self-publishers may find it difficult to come up with finished EPUBs. EPUBs are essentially packages containing HTML, CSS, and Javascript. In a sense, an EPUB is a small, self-contained website, and EPUB readers are offline, limited browsers. HTML, therefore, is already an input format that Manifold understands and can work with. What this means is that any document type that can easily be converted to HTML can likely be consumed by Manifold and made available to readers. We refer to the process of slurping a book up into Manifold as "Ingestion." Manifold can be extended by adding ingestion strategies to it. An ingestion strategy tells Manifold how to map a source document—eg, an EPUB—to a format it can understand. In short, we've anticipated that we'll want to ingest other kinds of documents and have left places where other developers can create their own strategies.&nbsp;With the aim of testing out this approach and also furthering our goal of increasing Manifold's user base, we spent a couple days writing a Markdown strategy that supports the GitBook format. This means that users will be able to feed Manifold a set of nested Markdown documents, which Manifold will then be able to make available online, just as it does an EPUB. Manifold's documentation, for example, is authored following the GitBook format, and it can now be read within Manifold itself. Three cheers for eating our own dog food! Backend Development Since I last posted, we've also been hard at work at building out the backend interfaces. Most of the basic backend HTML and CSS has been completed, and we're now in the process of developing reusable patterns and components in React to wire up the backend forms to the API. This has been challenging, as there is a lot of functionality required in Manifold's admin interface, and figuring out how to model the requisite state while keeping in our Flux architecture has required some thinking. We're close on this, with some initial proof of concept work, which I'll be discussing more in subsequent posts. That's it for today! We'll be posting&nbsp;more updates (hopefully with screenshots and some design comps) later this week. &nbsp; &nbsp;]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[This Week in Manifold: Team meeting, Numerous Fixes]]></title>
        <id>thisweekinmanifoldteammeetingnumerousfixes</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/thisweekinmanifoldteammeetingnumerousfixes"/>
        <updated>2016-11-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This has been an exciting week for Manifold. The UMNP team—Terence, Dan, Susan, and Doug—and Matt all came out to Portland for one of our regular meetings. We met at the Cast Iron Coding office in the old Washington High School building and spent two days talking through issues, thinking about Manifold use cases, sorted through thorny metadata and DOI concerns, and generally reviewed how far we've come, where we're at, and what's left to do. I always find these meetings inspiring and invigorating, and am reminded of what a strong team we have in place for this project. In the two weeks leading up to this meeting, the development and design team at Cast Iron has been working furiously to tighten up existing behavior and progress on the project resources. As a result, we don't have a lot in the way of big new features to report for this sprint. We do, however, have a long list of fixes, small improvements, and tweaks, which I'm including below. Next week is a short week, and I likely won't post an update until the following week. In the next sprint, we'll be finalizing project resources, and then turning our attention back to the annotation user interface, and begin work on comment threads. The release that went out to staging today includes the following revisions. Backend]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading with Susan Doerr]]></title>
        <id>readingwithsusandoerr</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/readingwithsusandoerr"/>
        <updated>2016-11-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[While the seismic ruptures of the election have unsettled the ground beneath us, it feels necessary to continue working on projects that look beyond the next four years, that address the possibility of connecting people through ideas and through constructive debate. Last&nbsp;week, in the midst of national turmoil, I had the pleasure of interviewing Susan Doerr, University of Minnesota Press Assistant Director, Digital Publishing and Operations. During our phone call, I asked Susan a number of questions about her thoughts on reading and the Manifold platform.I started by asking Susan what matters most to her about Manifold. She talked about the process of collaborating with the Manifold team on writing the grant proposal, and thinking about publishing books in the browser. Susan believes the real revolution of an epub or pdf ebook is the speed of distribution -- instant access for a reader. Susan said, “ebook reading devices are siloed -- a reader is stuck in an app or device.” What the Manifold team wanted to do was “break free from that constraint. Ebooks today are replications of print -- active media that don't do much more than the print edition of a book. And we wanted to do more.”Publishing a book in the browser allows it to be dynamic -- vs static. The more they thought about it, the more opportunity they saw for readers to follow a project as it evolve because Manifold can publish a project iteratively, that is, in pieces over time.]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[This Week in Manifold: DevOps, Infrastructure, and Social Activity]]></title>
        <id>thisweekinmanifolddevopsinfrastructureandsocialactivity</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/thisweekinmanifolddevopsinfrastructureandsocialactivity"/>
        <updated>2016-11-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thanks for joining me for another installation of "This Week in Manifold." First off, please accept my apologies for missing last week's update. When last Friday rolled around, we had a number of updates ready to go out to our staging site. However, when it was time to deploy, we hit a few unexpected problems. DevOps, Hosting Manifold, and Deployment This release adds a new metadata field to projects. Because the exact metadata requirements are difficult to pin down and may change from press to press, we wanted a relatively flexible approach to storing project, text, and resource metadata. Back in the day, we might have used an EAV model for this, but there are many well-documented drawbacks to that model. Because Manifold uses PostgreSQL as its database backend, we have access to a variety of field types for storing arbitrary amounts of data. In the past, we've used HSTORE for storing key/value pairs, but&nbsp;in this case we wanted something more flexible that could store different data types (HSTORE stores strings, but we want to store integers, boolean values, strings, arrays, etc). Recent versions of PostgreSQL include the JSONB field type, which is exactly what we want in this case. Alas, that meant that the October 28th&nbsp;release required&nbsp;some infrastructure updates. Sure, we could have shelled into the staging server and done a quick upgrade, but that's not how we roll on this project. It's really important to us that it be possible to easily provision hosts for Manifold, which means automating as much as possible. As Manifold grows, it relies on more and more services to run, which makes setting it up increasingly complex. With this release, Manifold needs all of the following configured on the server to run correctly:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Joining Manifold]]></title>
        <id>joiningmanifold</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/joiningmanifold"/>
        <updated>2016-10-31T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Halloween!My name is Jojo Karlin and I am an English doctoral student and Digital Fellow at the Graduate Center, CUNY. I’ve joined Manifold this fall to help get the word out about what the team has been up to, and I am excited to investigate the generative potential built into this iterative, collaborative platform. I love the ways Manifold seeks to enrich scholarly publication by building communities of researchers engaged in collective annotation and networked reading.When friends and acquaintances unfamiliar with the field hear I work in “digital humanities,” they often react with anxieties about the death of print. Skeptical bibliophiles lament the impact of screens on humanity as they cite popular science articles about babies swiping pages of print books. &nbsp;Yet I remain a stalwart defender of books in their many forms. I grew up in a house lined with books and have a categorical weakness for library book sales and department book swaps; I also depend on my computer and smartphone as part of my reading practice.Books, even print-only, are not single-use -- people come to them and at them from different angles and at different times. I believe that the many ways we read books should be simultaneously available and that ideas deserve the full range of available outlets and expression. What I particularly love about Manifold is the way it bridges print and digital forms, giving presses and authors the opportunity to benefit from affordances of both -- utilizing digital features while reinforcing the value of print-based scholarship. Since joining Manifold, I have begun to see how the team approaches the transformations of text in recent years, the influx (sometimes numbing inundation) of social media, and the existing endeavors of numerous presses to engage scholarship digitally. “Building Manifold” gives me a sense of Manifold’s dual purpose-- platform construction and conceptual restructuring -- and Zach’s updates describe incremental decisions of development. By taking pains to publicly share the process of creating the tool, the Manifold team participates in the kind of transparent teamwork that the tool itself proposes. I look forward to sharing my perspective as well.In the coming months, I will help to surface some of the exciting progress that the team has been making. I will post updates about design, interviews with team members, and reflections on some of the trickier conceptual decisions. Even jumping in now, I have found the whole team -- Susan, Zach, Matt, Doug, Terence, Naomi, everyone!-- to be wonderfully welcoming and warm. I am looking forward to learning more, and I hope you will share in my excitement. If you have questions about Manifold, sign up for our newsletter, follow/star/love our git repository, follow @ManifoldScholar on Twitter, and feel free to get in touch. Thanks and be well,Jojo]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[This Week in Manifold: Project Detail Improvements]]></title>
        <id>thisweekinmanifoldprojectdetailimprovements</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/thisweekinmanifoldprojectdetailimprovements"/>
        <updated>2016-10-24T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to a new regular feature on the Building Manifold blog Our staging instance of Manifold is currently on a private server. However, we'll be opening it up to the public in a few&nbsp;weeks, as soon as we're able to load an initial set of texts with open access rights onto the platform. Once that happens, it will be possible for readers of this blog to check out our weekly builds for themselves. Our last development sprint focused on tightening up existing code, mainly around the project detail view. Notable changes included the following: Refactoring]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting Points with the Manifold Digital Projects Editor]]></title>
        <id>startingpointswiththemanifolddigitalprojectseditor</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/startingpointswiththemanifolddigitalprojectseditor"/>
        <updated>2016-06-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[As Jason indicated in this space earlier, Manifold is not simply an endeavor to create a better publishing platform; it is an answer to the challenge of rethinking and reframing the concept of scholarly publishing. In broad strokes, scholarly publishing is very much still a print-centric enterprise. Despite the vast libraries of electronic publications available, the systems, mindsets, and expectations of the greater university press culture—including those of authors and the academy—are engineered specifically for print.In terms of production, while many presses have augmented their procedures over the past two decades, those alterations tend to simply mirror print methods instead of refashioning them to account for digital materials and platforms. For other presses, third-party service providers, or packagers, handle the creation of electronic editions in parallel with print or as an afterthought to it. That is to say, even when print isn’t to be the only medium of publication, it still receives primacy over all other editions. When a question of formatting comes up, it’s a question to be resolved for print first. When internal elements are being scrutinized, they are done through a lens that foremost anticipates a static physical object.We’ve reached a moment, however, when we need to step back from print and see it in the proper context among the myriad means of expression scholars now have at their disposal. And it’s time to grapple with the fact that scholarly publishing involves more than books, more than journals, more than print. It’s not tied to paper; it’s not a function of the software it passes through. Instead, it’s the expression of content in the most meaningful and impactful ways possible. In that context, university presses must become adaptive and able to treat materials that aren’t always easily categorized or codified just as well as they do traditional vehicles like a journal or monograph.That is no small thing. The print paradigm has been refined and honed for generations. It is deeply ingrained, predicating the workings of every department within a press. Reengineering it is not something that will happen overnight. Nor should it. But nor should we let the print mold stand as a boulder, cordoning off those modes of expression that weren’t possible a few years ago or those just over the horizon. Exploring those opportunities is the commitment of the Manifold team. We bring together the perspectives of the university press, the scholar, and the technologist to hone in on new ways presses can present scholarship, realistically adapt existing procedures to account for a broad spectrum of publishing output, and technically deliver those varied means of expression to the readership in ways they are expecting as well as in ways they are not.As the Manifold digital projects editor, I am working closely with the platform developers at Cast Iron Coding, our partners at the GC Digital Scholarship Lab, authors, and press staff across departments here at Minnesota to help craft, test, and document replicable processes that will allow presses to shift from a publishing plan with a very specific terminus to one that celebrates projects as a spectrum of scholarly publication. In the weeks and months ahead, I’ll be returning here to talk more about the implications of that and the challenges we’re working through as we move from platform wireframes into more robust test cases.Stay tuned. The fun is just starting!—Terence Smyre, Manifold Digital Projects Editor]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts from Editors and Authors on What Makes a Good Manifold Project]]></title>
        <id>thoughtsfromeditorsandauthorsonwhatmakesagoodmanifoldproject</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/thoughtsfromeditorsandauthorsonwhatmakesagoodmanifoldproject"/>
        <updated>2016-01-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[As Manifold Scholarship progresses through its first rounds of wireframes, editors at the University of Minnesota Press are already discussing the platform with authors and considering book projects. Manifold will have an impact on the full span of a project, from the early stages of researching and collecting data for a book, to the drafting of a proposal, to peer review and press evaluation, and across the iterative stages of a manuscript’s organic development leading to the peer reviewed, published edition. Just as Manifold is designed to transform the nature of scholarly publishing, we are also asking scholars, from their earliest articulations, to think elastically about the ways in which Manifold can expand their project beyond the static, physical book. As I’ve been asking editors and press authors to describe what makes a project suitable for publication on Manifold, I’ve found myself reflecting on the limitations the traditional print book can impose on scholars. One could argue that the traditional print scholarly monograph isn’t an accurate record of a research project. The fixed form of the book, for example, doesn’t reflect the long duration of research, the months of ethnography, the full compliment of data collection and archival deep-dives. The monograph doesn’t record the full chorus of voices that help shape a project, such as the feedback of colleagues and peers. Research is already iterative, benefitting from community dialogue and from interfacing with an array of media. It’s just that the current way of disseminating that research doesn’t reflect those pre-publication engagements. Up to now, when authors have wanted to share with readers materials that can’t fit into a print book such as audio and video files, teaching tools, or archival materials, they have often had to host them on a disconnected website. There’s often little travel between the website and the physical book, and these websites quickly fade away, disconnected by link rot or taken down from university servers when a scholar switches institutions. But these objects are never ancillary—they are part and parcel of the work itself. One potential Manifold author remarked to me that the traditional book doesn’t offer readers the chance to review the primary materials and say, “I disagree.” Manifold will allow authors to embed these objects within or alongside the text so that readers can chart their own course through all the elements that make up a scholarly book and research project. This feature is especially important to Manifold author Mara Mills, assistant professor of media, culture and communication at New York University. Mills was initially attracted to Manifold because it provided an opportunity to develop an accessible multimedia publication:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Technical Introduction to Manifold]]></title>
        <id>atechnicalintroductiontomanifold</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/atechnicalintroductiontomanifold"/>
        <updated>2015-12-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hello Manifoldians! I'm Zach Davis, principle at Cast Iron Coding, a web development studio in Portland, Oregon. My team and I are responsible for UX design, visual design, and development of Manifold over the course of the grant, and it is my hope that I'll be able to post regular updates here&nbsp;detailing development and design decisions, challenges, and milestones over the course of the project. For now, however, I'd like to walk through the technology stack we've settled on, and the reasoning behind some of these choices. If anyone has any questions, please don't hesitate to post a comment! Where to find the source code As you know, one of the requirements of the grant funding this development is that Manifold be released as open source, and our current plan is to release Manifold under the GPLv3. For the time being, Manifold source code is stored in the ManifoldScholar/manifold Github repository. If you look at the ManifoldScholar GitHub organization, you'll see additional repositories for Manifold-API and Manifold-Client. Eventually, we&nbsp;hope to be able to provide the Manifold API as a stand-alone piece of software that can be used to parse, store, and expose ePub and Markdown documents over a RESTful API. In preparation for this, we're using a git subtree-split strategy to break the Manifold project into separate API and Client packages. These split repositories are updated significantly less frequently than the main Manifold repository. If your goal is to follow our development, for now your best bet will be to just watch the primary repository. We've already made significant progress on Manifold, although we're still far from an alpha release. We'd&nbsp;love it if you'd show your support for our project by starring our GitHub repo and keeping an eye on development. As we get closer to a stable alpha release in 2016, we'll invite community members to download and install their own instance of Manifold. Server-side&nbsp;architecture Manifold is split into the client application, and the server-side application. For now, these two applications share a repository to simplify development, but they are very distinct and meant to run independently of each other. The server-side application is built in Ruby and Rails. Specifically, we're using what is currently edge Rails, and what will soon be Rails 5. The development team&nbsp;thought long and hard about what server-side language to use, which was mainly a debate about the relative merits of using Ruby or Javascript on the server. While we have many years of experience working with PHP, and understand that it is still a popular, easy choice among academic developers, we felt strongly that the advantages of Ruby—strong OOP support, support for more functional styles, cleaner and more consistent syntax, and the maturity of Rails—outweighed the&nbsp;disadvantages of&nbsp;a more complex execution model and smaller (but by no means&nbsp;small) developer community. Laravel, the current leading PHP framework, for all its notable strengths, lacks the completeness and maturity of Rails and Active Record. Our choice to go with edge rails, rather than stable Rails 4.x, was driven by the fact that our server-side component is only serving an API, and Rails 5 will eventually ship with an api-only flag. This means that many aspects of Rails—the view layer, sprockets, etc—have been removed, making for a more lightweight framework overall. Another strong reason for choosing Rails was the presence of a strong HTML/XML parsing library in Nokogiri. Manifold deals heavily (but not exclusively) in EPUBs, which are HTML documents. To pull those documents apart and recreate them in the browser, we need a powerful parsing tool, which we've found in Nokogiri. The server side application exposes a REST style API to be consumed by the client. This API conforms to the style and conventions laid out by Steve Klabnik, Yehuda Katz, Dan Gebhardt, Tyler Kellen, and Ethan Resnick in the JSON API Specification. While it's important that developers expose all the things with APIs, it's challenging when each API follows its own idiosyncratic conventions. One of our goals on this project is to&nbsp;make Manifold as easy as possible to integrate into a presses existing infrastructure and environment, and following an established API specification helps us with that goal.&nbsp;Because the Manifold client application consumed Manifold's public API, integrators can be sure that the API is well tested and reliable. Authentication against the API will be handled&nbsp;using JSON Web Tokens (JWT).&nbsp;It will also be possible for a user to generate an API token by logging in through an OAuth provider such as Twitter or Facebook. **Client-side architecture** If we made a safe, conservative choice in Rails on the server-side, we've taken more of a leap on the client-side. The Manifold client is a single page application (SPA) that is built on React and Redux. Both are relatively new Javascript libraries (or frameworks, depending on how you look at things) that are rapidly gaining mindshare and popularity among front-end developers. For those who are unfamiliar, React is a Javascript library that simplifies the process of creating reusable components. Unlike other popular libraries such as Angular or Knockout, React does not attempt to solve the problem of two-way data binding. Instead, it is meant to be used with a specific&nbsp;architecture called Flux, which is structured around one-way data flow and immutability. Both React and Redux have a relatively small surface area. Redux APIs are small, and the library as a whole is under 15k. At Cast Iron, we've worked with many Javascript frameworks, in particular Angular and Backbone. Over time, client-side development has become quite complex, and it's our feeling that while Angular can work well on some projects, it doesn't do enough to reduce that complexity. By restricting the way in which data can flow through the application, and abstracting away the asynchronicity that can make client-side development challenging, we've found Redux and React to be a powerful combination that allows us to iterate quickly without sacrificing quality or maintainability. There are some challenges that come with developing a single page javascript application. For our purposes, the biggest challenge is to ensure that there is content loaded on the page before the javascript executes. We feel strongly that Manifold needs to be accessible to users with disability, to search engine crawlers, to screen readers, etc, and that we can't count on a javascript environment. For this reason, the Manifold client will be served by a small Node/Express application running on the server. Most of the javascript that executes in the browser is built to be isomorphic (now also known&nbsp;as universal), which means that care has been taken to ensure that it can be executed in a server-side context (node) and in a client-side context (the browser). The practical outcome of this approach is that the server-side component will be able to fully render the HTML before sending the page to the client, which solves the many accessibility and SEO problems. The advantages to the SPA approach are, well, manifold. The application will feel very fast, and we'll be vastly reducing the amount of data that's sent over the network. Complex UI elements, like the annotation pieces, will be have a much more stable, testable framework backing them. There will be more room for reusable components, and&nbsp;the various state-changes that can occur in the client-side application will be well tested. While we're diving in head-first on React + Redux, we are not, for now, following the current trend of doing only inline-CSS. For the time being, we'll be using the SASS preprocessor for all styles. At the language level, we're relying heavily on ES6 and upcoming ES7 features. We're using Babel to transpile ES6+ code down to ES5 &nbsp;so that it will run in IE9+, Firefox, and Safari. By using edge Javascript language features, our hope is that to some degree we will future proof Manifold code. For now, we're limiting ourselves to ES6+ features that are at stage 1 or greater, and acknowledge that there is some risk even with stage 1. We rely heavily on NPM for package management, and Webpack for transpiling assets during development, and for building assets for production. At Cast Iron, we've used Grunt and Gulp on other projects, but it looks to us like the React community is gravitating toward Webpack, and for good reasons. On Manifold, it's being used for automatically linting our code, for generating icon fonts from SVG icons, for transpiling ES6+ to ES5, and Sass to CSS. Testing Tests are important. They build confidence and help us to refactor without regressions. While we don't always follow test-driven-development practices, we do feel that it's important to have a robust test suite in place. On the API side, we're using rspec for tests. On the client-side we will be using Mocha. Server infrastructure and continuous integration DevOps and infrastructure automation are essential to our workflow at Cast Iron. We use Boxen to setup development instances of projects, and we use Puppet to deploy applications to staging and production environments. Our manifests for deploying Manifold are still in progress, but they're close. Soon, I hope to have a staging environment that's updated regularly via Jenkins, our continuous integration server.&nbsp;Soon, we'll also have Travis build notifications in place on the Github repository. To run Manifold, you'll need to have the following setup on a server:]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Opening Access: The Reinvention of the Academic Book]]></title>
        <id>openingaccessthereinventionoftheacademicbook</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/openingaccessthereinventionoftheacademicbook"/>
        <updated>2015-11-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[On Tuesday, November 10, I was very happy to participate in an online conversation&nbsp;convened by the&nbsp;Association of American University Presses (AAUP) on the topic of "Opening Access//www.youtube.com/watch?v=SMXc-xwbRy0 From AAUP the model for access to scholarship (we might think of this as "who pays?") and the format or process for "publishing" scholarship (particularly in the long-form focused fields of the humanities and social sciences.) As University Press Week is celebrated, and as part of the Academic Book Week Great Debate series, AAUP is sponsoring an online discussion between thinkers and practitioners swimming in both streams. Moderated by Jennifer Howard (Chronicle of Higher Education), the conversation will include Frances Pinter (Manchester University Press/Knowledge Unlatched), a publisher of both traditional print and innovative Open Access monographs; Peter Suber (Harvard University Berkman Center for Internet & Society), one of the foremost theorists of Open Access; Augusta Rohrbach (author of Thinking Outside the Book), a scholar of book culture embedded in a world of digital communications; and Matthew K. Gold (CUNY Graduate Center), who, with the team on the Manifold project, is transforming scholarly publications into living digital works. -- Matthew K. Gold]]></summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building Manifold]]></title>
        <id>buildingmanifold</id>
        <link href="https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/buildingmanifold"/>
        <updated>2015-10-22T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to&nbsp;Building Manifold, a blog that will document the process of creating&nbsp; Manifold Scholarship , a&nbsp;project at the&nbsp;University of Minnesota Press in partnership with the&nbsp;GC Digital Scholarship Lab&nbsp;at the&nbsp;Graduate Center, CUNY&nbsp;and&nbsp;Cast Iron Coding. Manifold Scholarship is funded through a generous grant from the&nbsp;Andrew W. Mellon Foundation&nbsp;as part of a series of&nbsp;2015 grants made to university presses. Manifold Scholarship is composed of two parts The Manifold beta is now available!!]]></summary>
    </entry>
</feed>