<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Manifold Docs Blog</title>
        <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog</link>
        <description>Manifold Docs Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[#NextUP: Manifold: Digital Publishing as a Thing of Beauty]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/digital-publishing-beauty</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/digital-publishing-beauty</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This year’s #UPWeek coincides with a meeting of the Manifold Team—representatives from the three founding partners, the CUNY Graduate Center, Cast Iron Coding of Portland, OR, and the University of Minnesota Press. We’ll all be meeting halfway between Portland and NYC in Minneapolis, seeing each other in person for the first time since the pandemic began.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Belated Version 7 Update]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/v7-update</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/v7-update</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A belated update on the Version 7 release: We were so thrilled to share Manifold version 7.0 with our community in August. Our developers at Cast Iron Coding have put an incredible amount of time and care into the latest release, one of our biggest yet, which continues to build in new features and capabilities that have been requested by our users.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifold Community Meetup Recap]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/community-meetup-recap</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/community-meetup-recap</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[One of the highlights of 2021 was that we held our first quarterly Manifold Community Meetup. Something we love about building Manifold is seeing all of the amazing projects and initiatives that Manifold makes possible across the different groups and institutions who use it. At the same time, we found that publishers using Manifold often asked us for a means through which to discover what other Manifold instances are up to and how they have solved common challenges and obstacles. And so we inaugurated Manifold Community Meetups: a quarterly virtual meetup for Manifold community members to share practices, discuss strategies, ask questions, troubleshoot difficulties, and learn from each other.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifold Welcomes Six New Publishers]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/welcome-new-publishers</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/welcome-new-publishers</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The Manifold Team is delighted to announce the six publishers who will be joining the Manifold community in 2022 with grant-funded support packages, thanks to generous funding from The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Log4j2 Vulnerability]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/log42j</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/log42j</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Good afternoon, everyone!]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OA Week 2021 Project Spotlight 4]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/oa-week-2021-project-spotlight-4</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/oa-week-2021-project-spotlight-4</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The Mill on The Floss]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OA Week 2021 Project Spotlight 3]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/oa-week-2021-project-spotlight-3</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/oa-week-2021-project-spotlight-3</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The Negro and The Nation]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OA Week 2021 Project Spotlight 2]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/oa-week-2021-project-spotlight-2</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/oa-week-2021-project-spotlight-2</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The Greater Chaco Landscape]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OA Week 2021 Project Spotlight 1]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/oa-week-2021-project-spotlight-1</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/oa-week-2021-project-spotlight-1</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[As part of Open Access Week, Manifold is featuring interviews with the creators of exemplary projects that use Manifold's capabilities to the fullest. Our first installment in this series is Race &/ in America. We interviewed Allison Levy from Brown University Library Center for Digital Scholarship about this impressive project.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fall 2021 Accessibility Sprint!]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/fall21-accessibility-sprint</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/fall21-accessibility-sprint</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[At Manifold, we treat accessibility as a top-tier concern. Our developers at Cast Iron Coding are accessibility experts who design and develop the application with accessible functionality foremost in mind. In addition to the extensive testing they do in-house using screen-readers and browser add-ons, we’ve had the benefit of collaborating with the University of Washington’s library, press, and accessibility office over the past three years. The Washington team has performed an ongoing audit of Manifold over that time, and our two groups meet regularly to discuss new ideas and strategies for making the application even more performant for readers and content creators using assistive technologies.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifold v6.0 is available now!]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifold-v6</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifold-v6</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The latest version includes a new analytics feature, improved Word ingestion, global stylesheets, and more.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifold Moves Toward Sustainability, Promotes Learning and Equity with Two Major Grants]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldnextsteps</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifoldnextsteps</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The digital publication platform Manifold Scholarship will enter a new phase of its development, supported by two major grants, one from The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation and one from the National Endowment for the Humanities, allowing Manifold to solidify its structure for future sustainability and to expand its work as a leading provider of digital Open Educational Resources (OERs). Manifold, a collaboration between the GC Digital Scholarship Lab at the CUNY Graduate Center, Cast Iron Coding, and the University of Minnesota Press, is an open-source platform that enables publishers to create media-rich, interactive digital publications and extend the educational benefits and access of this scholarship to more communities. “Manifold is an innovative platform that exemplifies the University’s vision of integrated research and teaching,” says Chris Cramer, Vice President for Research at the University of Minnesota.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Access Granted: Manifold 5.0 Is Here!]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/accessgranted</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/accessgranted</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[We are delighted to announce the release of Manifold version 5.0, which is available for download here! The centerpiece of this release, a new Access Controls feature, will allow users to limit access to selected projects on a Manifold installation.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Happy holidays from Manifold!]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/happyholidaysfrommanifold</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/happyholidaysfrommanifold</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Here's to 2019! The Manifold Team sends good wishes to all as we head into the shortest day of the year and turn toward 2020. I've asked each team member to share a good memory from the year, a Manifold gift (be it moment with someone in the community, a favorite feature, a resolution). We're happy to be working together and with all of you.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Affordable Learning Georgia]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightaffordablelearninggeorgia</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightaffordablelearninggeorgia</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In the last training of the season, Terence met with Jeff Gallant, Program Manager of Affordable Learning Georgia; Joy Woodson, Assistant Director for Marketing Communications; and Lucy Harrison, Assistant Vice Chancellor for Library Services and Executive Director of GALILEO.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: University of Georgia Press]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightuniversityofgeorgiapress</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightuniversityofgeorgiapress</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Last week, Manifold Digital Projects Editor Terence was at the University of Georgia Press—the oldest and largest publisher in Georgia—exploring new digital initiatives and publishing models with Director Lisa Bayer and Executive Editor of Scholarly and Digital Publishing Mick Gusinde-Duffy.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Black Women and Religious Cultures]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightblackwomenandreligiouscultures</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightblackwomenandreligiouscultures</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This week we find Manifold Digital Projects Editor Terence in Atlanta meeting with Dr. Rosetta E. Ross. Dr. Ross, along with members of Spelman College's Department of Philosophy and Religious Studies and the Daughters of the African Atlantic community, is creating a new journal entitled Black Women and Religious Cultures. The journal seeks to examine the roles of religions, positively and negatively, in the lives of Black women, transnationally. In addition to publishing meeting proceedings from the Consultation of African and African Diasporan Women in Religion and Theology, the journal will include articles from participants in their growing community, facilitating an exchange of knowledge.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Arte Publico Press]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightartepublicopress</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightartepublicopress</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In this post, we find our digital projects editor, Terence, traveling to Houston, Texas, to meet with the Arte Público Press digital team: Executive Editor Gabriela Baeza Ventura, Carolina Villarroel of the Recovering the US Hispanic Literary Heritage Project, and Digital Programs Manager Lorena Gauthereau. The conversation revolved primarily around their recovery mission, the presses digital initiatives, as well as intro publications aimed at younger members of the Latino community. And, of course, all the amazing cuisine that Houston has to offer.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Lapham's Quarterly]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightlaphamsquarterly</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightlaphamsquarterly</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This week brought Terence from one Manifold hub to another, New York City, to meet with Elizabeth Della Zazzera, Digital Producer, and Jaime Fuller, Web Editor, at Lapham’s Quarterly.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manifold Digital Services Spotlight: Intermezzo]]></title>
            <link>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightintermezzo</link>
            <guid>https://manifoldscholar.github.io/manifold-docusaurus/blog/manifolddigitalservicesspotlightintermezzo</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In this post, we find our digital projects editor, Terence, traveling to the University of Kentucky to meet with Intermezzo editors Jeff Rice, Eric Detweiler, and Sergio C. Figueiredo. The conversation revolved around integrating Manifold with their series, which encourages writers to experiment with form, style, content, and approach to break down the barrier between the scholarly and the creative.]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>